good evening everybody
all right i wanna i'm gonna read
some heraclitus and um
see see if we can kind of get to
and think through the logos and the
deepest sense of the word and i'm i'm
reading
i'm reading this from um
evo de janeiro principles of philosophy
this is his translation of um
the what is this this fragment 50.
you know apparently i've been reading a
bunch of different
interpretations or translations
there's so many different ways that
things are translated but what i'm
liking about
um this translation is he and as far as
i can tell is taking it
taking the translation
back to the original
ancient greek understanding
of being right so
i think you take great take great pain
to not
um bring in like
cartesianist thinking and different
thinkings that
in presuppositions that were laid out
after
after heraclitus so um
his translation just seemed mind-blowing
to me actually
okay so this one
it reads provided you listen
not to me
but gather yourself into
the gathering itself
in accordance and gathering
gives rise to the fitting knowledge
all atones one i'll read that again
provided you listen not to me
but gather yourself
into the gathering
itself in accordance
and gathering gives rise
to the fitting knowledge
one atones all
so i'll read that one more time provided
you
you listen not to me but gather yourself
into the gathering itself in accordance
in gathering gives rise to the fitting
knowledge
one atones all
gives a shorter interpretation here too
um
a shorter translation listening not
to me but owning
to the gathering agreement
on the same fair knowledge
breaks one all
so
this one atones all
you know it's interesting because i
think first reading you know you can
kind of hear that as
i probably had a less fitted
hearing would it be to hear
that the logos is simply
hearing the one as if the logos is like
in the one
and to listen to the logos is to listen
to
that all things are one
however if you think about it if that
were the case
there would be there'd be uh the first
part of the fragment wouldn't need to
exist right
so it's like provide provided you listen
not to me
right so that's the first hint and
hearing it but
gather yourself and i think in this
sense
the gather yourself being
you can imagine like the soul or the
psyche
right yourself gathering
into the gathering itself or the logos
so
the psyche gathering itself
into the gathering itself of logos so
psyche
logos there's that relationship
in accordance in
gathering this accord right this
relationship
psyche and logos in gathering
gives rise to the fitting knowledge
right so the fitting knowledge this
accord
this the the soul or the psyche
gathers into the gathering as such i.e
the logos
in accordance in gathering gives
rise to the fitting knowledge
one atones all right so all of that
but you know before all that before one
atones all
if the one was simply there and
the logos was in the one right you
wouldn't need to
have a psyche in a gathering an
accordance and a fitted knowledge and
you wouldn't have to make sure that you
weren't listening to
heraclitus but listening to the logos no
it's
there's something at stake
in our listening to the logos
which affords something like the one
atoning all so
what i when i when i take this to me is
really interesting when you think about
this because
it shows that
the logos
is heard through our participation with
right and our participation with the
logos the
you could say the little uh little l
logos
right relates to the big l logos
that that in first of all it
it it presupposes that it doesn't have
to be this way so in other words i could
actually
end up just hearing you right the
speaker
if i just hear the speaker i'm not going
to hear the logos he's making a
distinction there so
i think the distinction is is the one
between
hearing and listening right what is it
to hear
what is to listen i think hearing
connotates
more of a surface sense like i can hear
the background music or i can hear the
ambient noise
right there's a there's a sense in which
i
i don't have to look into or listen into
what i'm hearing
right i can just hear it and it be given
and that's satisfactory enough right but
to listen
right it's something else listening
seems to
it seems to presuppose that i'm not i'm
not just hearing the words i'm not just
hearing
heraclitus right as what we're doing
right now
imagine is a kind of listening like
we're listening to
the logos which means i'm listening to
what isn't immediately apparent
right so i
i look at a parent and i comport myself
in such a way
i bring my psyche
right the my constitutional openness to
the logos to the world
and i can port i can port it in such a
in a listening way
such that my gathering is gathered
into the deeper
the deeper logos the deeper
intelligibility
that's gathering the particulars of the
appearance or
or or the words that are being spoken
and it's in that surrendering it's in
that
deeper listening that um
i get the sense that something catches
right my my
logos
i listen with my logos right
and in listening with the logos the
psyche
something catches and it like my
gathering
becomes gathered by the deeper
dynamic of intelligibility and then
through
that right a
fitting knowledge right
and i think the fittingness is this
speaks to this
um this
given potentiality of being right this
possibility
of psyche right this possibility of
being a human being
right which is an authentic one to be
authentically human to become a human
right in the aspirational sense right
the talos of human to unfold
with one's whole being to listen with
one's whole being to the world
in such a way that the gathering
of the psyche gathers the world such
that the deeper logos of the world
begins to gather the psyche and as that
happens
right this fitting relationship this
fitting knowledge
begins is is the way
that the one atones all so in other
words i can start to hear the
in the particulars of what i'm hearing
in the particulars of what's appearing
in the particular situation
right it's greater or
deeper meaning
that's concealed or withdrawn from the
surface of appearance
in some sense starts to
starts to you could say um
glow with the implicit deeper
structure of the unity of the world
right
in some sense it's like it's like the
difference between
you know hearing a bunch of noise
and of the individual notes of a song
and hearing music where in some sense
the individual notes
um
that appear
what i actually hear the harmony that i
hear
is the unity of the song itself but it's
it's not in the particular notes
right it's disclosed through the notes
right so i think what what what what
heraclitus is
pointing to with the logos is that there
is
that the unity of the world
not the totality right not just the
addition of all the parts
creating through totality but the
wholeness of
the world is a function of how we
participate authentically
right or kind of a radical listening
a radical openness to what is not
immediately apparent
right but one can learn to read
one can learn to listen one can learn to
open oneself in
gathering the world in such a way that
the gathering
of the logos itself becomes a fitted
knowledge such that
i can hear the music of the world i can
the the wholeness which
conceals in its conceals
in its withdrawals
from appearance in it allowing the
particular become manifest
of the whole right so in other words
that doesn't have to happen it's not
like the one is just
it's just is one and that's just waiting
for us to
you know pay attention to it no it's i
think it speaks to a participant as john
would say a participatory
knowing a authentic way of
being in the world and constituting it
with one's whole being
as a way of realizing the fullness of
the human being
as a being in the world right
but what what's interesting about this
if you really think about this is that
i think what heidegger is getting at
what all of the philosophers who talk
about nihilism
are getting at a lot of the sense of
nihilism
or the meaning crisis and all the
different ways that um
you know you can you can kind of say
that we don't listen
we and we don't we don't hear that we
don't listen
right
and the denialism today i'm
i believe this is what heidegger is
getting at is uh
is is the nihilism is a necessary
consequence of the of the
of the lack of listening to the logos
right
and because we hear heroclitus instead
of
the logos right we don't notice
that our whole lives
in some sense
only reveal beings right
and not being
and in that being the case another way
of saying that is that
the world only discloses as a
contingency
right we see things in the current
moment in the current person the current
relationship
the current school and the current
thing i have to do as a means
right contingent on something else
but the something else ends up becoming
the next contingency right so
a few generations of this and people
kind of grow up not even noticing
that they live in such a way
that they don't experience a moment in
which
being reveals itself is in its
non-contingency
and in its it discloses itself uh
in the truth of its own concealment in
in the thatness
right in the that there is god the sense
of wonderment is
is less and less able to be perceived
right in such a deep way i think this is
what i think is what they're getting at
with nihilism
right the notion of nihilism so
taking that into mind being mindful of
that right
how does one begin to
um respond to nihilism
right well i think the first thing is
that we probably need to start
hearing that we're not listening which
is not easy
listening is really interesting because
it's like to listen
i've noticed this and in
[Music]
in teaching people for years now
um the art of circling right listening
it's funny it's really difficult to like
i it's almost like to tell you how to
listen
is trying to tell someone how to how to
think
right for example if i were to ask you
how do you think a thought
you'll go well i just think it well no
but how do you think it
there's a there's a way in which the the
how
we think we just
think we don't know how we think we just
think
we live out how to think or being knows
how to think
right it's very much the case with
listening right
so you can't really teach somebody to
listen
i think what what ends up actually
happening
is that is that is that people make
listening explicit and then they go to
listen and then they start to hear that
they don't listen
and the moment that one hears that
they're not listening
is the moment the listening has begun
perhaps for the first time
right
it's so near and in
it's so near that it's it's a in its
nearness it's the most
remote and furthest away
that's where nihilism is right i think
is in that structure of nearness and the
structure of thinking and how we think
and
how we listen and therefore the risk is
always
the very act of trying to
the the very act of trying to solve
nihilism
right is often with the very
the very consciousness that causes it if
you will
so it's very tricky in this sense
so logos right i think
i think the very the very beginning
of philosophy really was with the
pre-socratics and i would say
logo seems to be i would say
heraclitus's thinking of
logos is the inception
of the thinking of being right and it
originally thought in its unity right
and and because of you know thousands of
years
of you could say the separation
of thought and being becomes more and
more separate
we have it's analogous to saying that
our connectedness with the world
right is mirrored by
our disconnection with
thinking and i mean in thinking not like
just you know
repetitive thoughts in your head i don't
mean that kind of thing i mean more like
the deeper sense of comportment to the
world
has become more and more separate we no
longer very rare like i just don't think
that people walk around with a sense in
which
um i'm
participating the world into a into
appearance
right like that the that my world is
banking on the way that i comport it
right there's a part it's a deep unified
participation in it right
i think there's a deep separation there
um that
that that was very difficult for people
to even notice anymore i think
that's the crisis right so
in addressing that right one of the
things i think
a return to heraclitus in the original
sense of
listening to the logos right
it starts to bank on being able
right to i just mean just kind of
thinking this through
is being able to have some sense of the
original notion of truth
right the the truth of being right which
is
really is um no longer the case
right we now see truth as correctness
whereas
the greeks originally saw the primordial
sense of truth was
the event of unconcealment or as um
evo de genero says um
disabscondedness it's quite a
funky word but there's a sense in which
to the truth is the event
of the unconcealedness
into appearance
a being of the world and that the deeper
things right in
what's interesting with with with this
is that
the deeper truths right cannot come
into their they can't be disclosed into
appearance just like we were talking
about with the
with the logos and and in the heraclitus
fragment in that
we have to listen to the appearance we
have to actually
hear and then listen to what we're
hearing
such that what can be unconcealed
elite alathea can be revealed
through um it
it can be flagrant in its
disabscondedness in other words it can
remain unconcealed like the sense of
wholeness
right but it glows through the part
and that it's truthness
belongs to concealment so in other words
now though we when we think about truth
we only really kind of see truth in
terms of correctness
or you know this kind of separation
between the world and the mind
right um where
the model of the world when it matches
the events in the world
that sense of correlation we call that
truth and that if it
doesn't and it doesn't correlate then
it's not
true whereas whereas in the
original notion of in early early greek
ancient greek something once
when something was less true right they
saw it as pseudo
right its appearance displayed less
of concealment right
in other words they still saw nothing
nothing still had being
in fact all the good stuff was in the
nothing it was not nothing it was the
it was the
the potential the possibility
out of which the world poured
and that truth was a way of comporting
oneself into
in some sense um
dancing with it out into more
truthness and conceal unconcealing
its concealedness so in other words
like poets really do understand and that
poetry
good poetry can reveal the unknown
without making it known they can reveal
the unknown as such
but reveal it and preserve it
in its unknownness that sense of
presence right or it's not
it's not forced into appearance
which is really like optimization this
is the sense of
the sense of utility right
seeing everything as a means to an end
or optimizing it or
extracting the energy out of it right
seeing everything as a resource
in order to do that you have to like you
have to really just relate to things in
a very shallow way
you can't really tend you can't tend to
the sense in which the deepest
truth of being is in its
is in its inability to reveal itself
in just its objective appearance
that the listening is the thing that can
listen to what's most silent
that's what it is it's that's that hum
of silence
thanks for listening